<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
                         "dtd/website.dtd" >

<webpage id="gimpcon2003-mins-3" lang="en">

  <head>
    <title>The Third Big Serious Meeting of GIMPCon 2003</title>
    <titleabbrev>Third Meeting</titleabbrev>
    <summary>Minutes of the third GIMPCon 2003 Meeting</summary>
  </head>

  <para>
    August 9th 2003, some time in the afternoon
  </para>

  <para>
    Here are the minutes of Yet Another Big Meeting that took place
    this afternoon in the GimpTent. The meeting was chaired by Dave
    Neary and these minutes were written by Raphaël Quinet.
  </para>

  <para>
    The title of this meeting was <quote>Communication</quote>. The
    main topics were how to improve the communication between
    developers and users or potential new developers. We also
    discussed how to present The GIMP to the <quote>outside</quote>
    and how to make it easier for new users to try out The GIMP or get
    involved in GIMP development.
  </para>

  <para>
    Altough there was no pre-defined agenda for this meeting,
    the following topics were discussed:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <link linkend="developers">How to get new developers?</link>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <link linkend="binary">De we need binary distributions?</link>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <link linkend="bugzilla">Is Bugzilla too hard to use for new
        users?</link>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <link linkend="tasks">List of open tasks</link>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <link linkend="mailinglists">Mailing lists</link>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <section id="developers">
    <title>How to get new developers?</title>

    <para>
      Like in any Free Software project, developers are leaving from
      time to time to pursue other projects. And from time to time,
      new developersare joining the team and starting to contribute.
      However, it looks like the number of new developers joining the
      GIMP development has been decreasing in the recent years. This
      may be due in part to the fact that there haven't been any major
      changes in a stable release for a long time.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another reason may be that it is difficult to build the
      development version because it depends on released versions of
      some libraries that are not included yet in the major GNU/Linux
      distributions (e.g., GTK+ version 2.2.2). Also, the number of
      dependencies for GIMP 1.3.x is much higher than the number of
      dependencies for GIMP 1.2.x, so it ismore difficult to have a
      working build environment for the 1.3.x version. This problem
      may be solved as time passes, because more and more
      distributions will include the required libraries.
    </para>

    <para>
      There should be a section on www.gimp.org or developer.gimp.org
      titled <quote>How to contribute?</quote> or <quote>How to get
      involved?</quote>. It should be easy for potential new
      developers to see where to start and how they can help. More on
      that below.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="binary">
    <title>Do we need binary distributions?</title>

    <para>
      There was a discussion about binary distributions. This may help
      people to try some versions of the GIMP (especially the
      development versions) without having to compile everything.
      However, maintaining binaries is a lot of work, even if we only
      maintain binaries supplied by others. In addition, this would
      bring some additional responsabilities that we do not want to
      have. For these reasons, it was decided that www.gimp.org would
      not host any binaries but would link to the pages of those who
      are providing binaries for various platforms.
    </para>

    <para>
      It would be very nice to have Windows binaries for the
      development version.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="bugzilla">
    <title>Is Bugzilla too hard to use for new users?</title>

    <para>
      It was suggested to make it easier for users to submit bug
      reports, for example by having an e-mail address to which bug
      reports can be sent without having to register to Bugzilla (we
      already have such an address, although it is not widely known).
      This proposal was rejected because most of the bug reports
      (especially from new users) are incomplete and require
      additional information. If the user does nothave a Bugzilla
      account, it is not possible to rely on the automatic
      notification system to send messages to the user when a comment
      is added to their bug report or when the status of their bug
      report changes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Most developers consider Bugzilla to be a very valuable tool
      that works well. Instead of trying to hide Bugzilla from the
      users, we should try to make it as easy as possible for the new
      users to join. This is already done to some extent by the bug
      submission wizard available from http://bugs.gimp.org/. There is
      a small problem with the GNOME2 keyword that prevents the open
      GIMP bugs from being displayed to the user and we should try to
      get this fixed.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="tasks">
    <title>List of open tasks</title>

    <para>
      There are many open bug reports or proposals for enhancements
      that would be relatively easy to fix or implement. We should
      make it easier for potential contributors to see the list of
      easy tasks that are open. The <quote>easy tasks</quote> should
      include anything that can be done in one or two hours by an
      average developer or maybe a bit more if the contributor is not
      familiar with the code.
    </para>

    <para>
      The best way to keep the list of open tasks up-to-date is
      probably to base it on Bugzilla. We could for example use a
      Bugzilla keyword for all bugs that are easy to fix (there is
      already a keyword <quote>easy-fix</quote> reserved for that,
      although we could invent our own). It would then be easy to
      create a Bugzilla query showing the list of easy tasks. Another
      solution would be to have a page on www.gimp.org or
      developer.gimp.org containing a list of all these bugs, with
      direct links to the corresponding bug reports. The second
      solution may require a bit more work because it would have to be
      maintained by someone, but it might be a bit easier to use.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="mailinglists">
    <title>Mailing lists</title>

    <para>
      Sometimes, there is a lack of communication between users and
      developers of The GIMP. After some discussion, it was decided
      that we should not merge the mailing lists gimp-user and
      gimp-developer because this could cause various problems: the
      combined amount of traffic may be too high for some subscribers,
      the discussions among developers may be confusing for some
      users, and in general we should let people subscribe to what
      they are interested in, instead of removing this option by
      merging the lists (we cannot force anybody to read what they do
      not want to read).
    </para>

    <para>
      But it would be very useful for the developers to get more
      feedback from the users, especially about UI and usability
      issues. For this reason, all developers are strongly encouraged
      to subscribe to the gimp-user list.
    </para>

    <para>
      The web site (www.gimp.org) should contain a list of the various
      sources of information about the GIMP: mailing lists, newsgroup,
      Yahoo group, GUG, other web sites such as linuxgraphic.org or
      gimp.de, etc. The description of the mailing lists should
      encourage people to subscribe to both the users and developers
      lists.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>
      We hope that the next stable release will attract new
      developers. This has been the case when 1.0 and 1.2 were
      released. The transition to the new web site will also help,
      especially if the navigation menu contains some useful items
      such as <quote>Bugs</quote>, <quote>FAQ</quote>, etc. The
      following items should be available in the web site:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <quote>How to contribute?</quote> or <quote>Getting involved</quote>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        List of tasks
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        List of sources of information (mailing lists, newsgroup, ...)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        FAQ
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      As with the other documents summarizing what is happening here
      at GimpCon, comments are welcome...
    </para>

    <para>
      Written by Raphaël Quinet
    </para>

  </section>

</webpage>
