<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
                         "dtd/website.dtd">

<webpage id="gimpcon2006" lang="en">
  
  <head>
    <title>The GIMP Developers Conference 2006</title>
    <titleabbrev>GIMPCon 2006</titleabbrev>
    <summary>This year's GimpCon</summary>
  </head>

  <para>
    The GIMP Developers Conference 2006 was held as a sub-event
    of the <ulink url="http://www.libregraphicsmeeting.org">Libre
    Graphics Meeting</ulink> in Lyon, France, on the 17th, 18th and
    19th of March.
  </para>

  <para role="images">
    <ulink url="people.jpg">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="people_small.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>The People at GIMPCon 2006</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </ulink>
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>About the GIMP Developers Conference</title>

    <para>
      The GIMP Developers Conference, also known as GIMPCon, is a
      gathering of GIMP and GEGL developers from all over the
      World. It is a vital opportunity for GIMP developers to meet
      each other and discuss the direction which the software will
      take over the coming years.
    </para>

    <para>
      There have been four GIMP Conferences previously: two in Berlin,
      Germany hosted by the CCC (the Chaos Computer Club), one in
      Kristiansand, Norway as part of GUADEC 2004 and one in
      Stuttgart, Germany as part of GUADEC 2005.
    </para>

   </section>

  <section>
    <title>Minutes of the GIMP Developers Conference 2006</title>

    <para>
      During LGM, we had two sessions dedicated to GIMP: one on
      Saturday afternoon (16:30-18:00) and one on Sunday
      (10:30-16:00). The following points were on the agenda:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="gimp24">GIMP 2.4</link>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="documentation">Documentation</link>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="gimp299">GIMP 2.99</link>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="developers">How to get more GIMP developers?</link>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="vision">GIMP vision</link>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para role="images">
      <ulink url="meetings.jpg">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="meetings_small.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Discussions and presentations at GIMPCon 2006</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </ulink>
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="gimp24">
    <title>GIMP 2.4</title>
   
    <section>
      <subtitle>SIOX</subtitle> 
      
      <para>Gerald explained the current status of SIOX and its future
      developments:

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            There are still some performance concerns because SIOX was
            designed mainly for web-sized images. In the morning,
            Raphaël suggested a way to add a low resolution preview
            for large images and this feature will be implemented
            soon.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Implement a detail refinement brush. Simon suggested to
            apply the refinement automatically on the edge area, but
            Gerald replied that defining such an area assumes that the
            shape is simple, which is something that SIOX tries to
            avoid.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            New preview toggle, which temporarily disables the
            automatic computation for multiple brush strokes for
            example.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            A volunteer for integrating more SIOX features in GIMP
            is needed.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <subtitle>New tools</subtitle>

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Sven pointed out that the rectangular and ellipse selection
            tools should have the same behavior.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The new align tool is also confusing for some users. Its
            behavior is still too flaky. Sven mentioned that Peter
            Sikking may be able to help in determining what the users
            want. A session with Peter is planned for tomorrow (the
            <link linkend="vision">vision discussion</link>).
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The code for the Lanczos interpolation is currently
            broken. Either we fix the Lanczos code or we hide it from
            the 2.4 release by removing it from the UI and from the
            PDB.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <subtitle>Google's Summer of Code</subtitle>

      <para>
        Dave pointed out that the Summer of Code is coming soon and
        ideas are needed. GIMP is one of the projects which can offer
        tasks to be solved.
      </para>
      <para>
        Ideas and Tasks are needed soon, probably around the beginning
        of May.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <subtitle>Preparation for the 2.4 release</subtitle>

      <para>
        Michael pointed out that some terms in the GIMP UI uses are
        misleading and very different from other image manipulation
        programs. One example is the misleading dpi instead of ppi.
      </para>

      <para>
        Michael proposed a Texttool PDB and also new features: multiple
        styles for a line of text, more control over text.
        Unfortunately, GIMP does not currently support all pango
        features. Sometimes ligature problems occur with Bitstream
        Vera Sans.
      </para>

      <para>
        Various other issues were also discussed: undo handling of
        vector operations, improvements to the full screen mode (some
        plug-ins cannot display progress bars), etc.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A list of blocker bugs for the 2.4 release is needed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A string and UI freeze is needed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Mitch's cleanup should not be commited before the 2.4
            release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Volunteers are needed for checking GIMP terms (English and
            translations). A wiki page should track the terms and also
            possible translations. One volunteer should elaborate if
            Rosetta from Ubuntu can be used for this.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A bug is needed for plug-ins which use g_message() and where
            dialogs pop up behind the main window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A volunteer is needed for the Texttool PDB.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="documentation">
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>
      The manual currently features nine languages, five are activly
      worked on. Russian and Norwegian will be added after the 0.10
      release. DocBook/XML is a barrier for new contributors, but there
      is currently no valuable alternative available.
    </para>

    <para>
      For PDF creation we should use dblatex instead of the dead project
      db2latex.
    </para>

    <para>
      The more translation an XML file holds the more difficult it is
      for contributors to concentrate on their content. Maybe we should
      split up the content directory-wise instead of profiling.
    </para>

    <para>
      Michael proposed way users can comment on HTML pages like the PHP
      documentation. The problems are: what will happen to comments
      after an update of the documentation, how and who manages
      comments, which system will suit our needs.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <title>TODO</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Stick to DocBook/XML for the next year. Be aware of the
          problems and change to a different internal structure if
          needed. A new project page should make it easier to
          contributors to join the project.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Elaborate which issue tracker can lower the barriers for
          feedback from our readers without turning it into a
	  discussion forum that needs active moderation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
 
  <section id="gimp299">
    <title>GIMP 2.99</title>

    <section>
      <subtitle>GEGL</subtitle>

      <para>
        Pippin pointed out that GEGL does not yet support calculation
        over regions of interest. Some of the code that does that is
        currently 8-bits only, but the reference buffer implementation
        would be 32bits float per pixel. Yosh proposed to generate all
        the code needed for this from a template.
      </para>

      <para>
        Pippin: GEGL is undead.
      </para>

      <para>
        Mitch suggested that the integration of GEGL should be in small
        steps. The plug-in API should be GEGL only, but will provide
        backwards compatibility from old plug-ins for 8bits only.
      </para>

      <para>
        UI and Usability problems are also caused by the indexed mode.
        We concluded that it should be available if the user exports
        his image to an indexed format, like GIF or PCX. For some indexed
        images, the order of the colors in the palette is significant.
        Raphaël proposed to handle these images through GEGL as 16bits
        images with the 8 least significant bits representing the
        original palette index so that it can be restored later when
        saving. Gerald mentioned that Apple may already be doing
        something similar.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Write the 32bits float version first, then generate others
            from that reference version.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Replace the code in the base directory by GEGL operations.
            First replace the image map tool (used for color correction,
            etc.) using GEGL adapters around the pixel buffers. Then
            later replace the layers and masks.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="developers">
    <title>How can we motivate people to join the GIMP development?</title>

    <para>
      The current project page for gimp.org is not really structured and
      not very easy to get in touch with the developers. It would
      help to show to the potential contributers a list of tasks that
      GIMP developers consider relatively easy and useful for the
      next version. We could also use the task list for the Google
      Summer of Code or for bounties, etc.
    </para>

    <para>
      We should make sure that people feel welcome when they read the
      GIMP mailing lists. For example, we should avoid criticizing
      those who mention GimpShop or commercial programs such as
      Photoshop.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some suggestions were discussed, such as introducing aging in
      the list of GIMP authors. The About dialog would first list
      those who contributed to the current version and then a longer
      list of previous contributers. Sven and Yosh remarked that we
      are not really using the mailing lists for discussing GIMP
      development. Most of the discussion happens on IRC or directly
      between people. This could be improved. There was also some
      debate about how to avoid pointless discussions on the gimp-web
      mailing list.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <title>TODO</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Setup a tasks list on the wiki of what can be achieved and
          implemented. It ranges from easy to very complex tasks. Each
          task should be linked to a bugzilla bug report. If someone
          starts working on one of these tasks, its bug report should
          be marked as ASSIGNED.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Improve the infrastructure for the web site and try to make
          contributions easier: simpler installation and testing, if
          possible without requiring special skills or permissions.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="vision">
    <title>GIMP vision</title>

    <para>
      Peter Sikking helped us to formulate a product vision for GIMP.
      The vision helps to define what standard installation of the
      GIMP is: what plug-ins are standard and what plug-ins are
      optional. It shouldn't be a simple cost-and-benefit analysis of
      what it means to support a feature. The current problem of the
      product vision is too broad to be practical. Peter proposes that
      our product vision should address a kind of Gauss curve of what
      users GIMP is made for. Currently we have the experts and newbies,
      but a low point for the intermediates.
    </para>

    <para>
      Good defaults would be chosen depending on our vision, not
      by inventing new scenarios for each thing that we want to
      evaluate. The user scenarios would be written down in advance.
      These scenarios should not be changed afterwards because it would
      lead to too much discussion. The goal is to cut down all this
      discussion. <emphasis role="bold">The product vision is to be used
      as a filter.</emphasis>
      For example: If someone comes with the request that the UI of GIMP
      should be like Photoshop, we can simply state: <quote>We are not
      trying to be like Photoshop, because we have a different product
      vision.</quote> Though, the feature requests should still be
      examined carefully.
    </para>

    <section>
      <subtitle>Targeted user base</subtitle>
      
      <para>
        GIMP targets experienced users. If we acknowledge that GIMP is
        not (primarily) for beginners, we cut off a lot of problems
        such as <quote>do we need to support that,</quote> etc.  Peter
        noted that a <quote>GIMP Light</quote> would not just have
        some options cut off from the menus: it would have a
        completely different user interface, even if it would use the
        same code under the hood.
      </para>

      <para>
        Some developers work on GIMP to promote the Free Software
        movement and would probably not contribute if GIMP was not
        free.  Others think that GIMP should provide fun for its
        developers, although our user base has grown a bit large for
        just doing fun experiments.  We have to acknowledge that we
        address a user base that may be more experienced in image
        manipulation than we are, so the developers are partially out
        of the target group.
      </para>

      <para>
        Before converging towards a definition of the GIMP target
        groups and GIMP vision, there were several discussions
        involving examples and use cases, whether GIMP should be the
        best image manipulation program in the universe (best for
        who?), whether those working on icons and those working on
        photos have the same needs (number of images open, relative
        sizes), whether people need to switch frequently between GIMP
        and other applications (browser or editor for web work),
        whether we will support painting with shapes and natural
        media, etc.
      </para>

      <para>
        Eventually, a GIMP vision emerged...
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <subtitle>What GIMP is:</subtitle>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is Free Software
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is a high-end photo manipulation application, and
            supports creating original art from images;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is a high-end application for producing icons,
            graphical elements of web pages, and art for user interface
            elements;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is a platform for programming cutting edge image
            processing algorithms, by scientists and artists;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is user-configurable to automate repetitive tasks;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP is easily user-extendable, by easy installation
            of plug-ins.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <subtitle>What GIMP is not:</subtitle>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>GIMP is not MS Paint or Adobe Photoshop</para> 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <itemizedlist>
      <title>TODO</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Make it easier to perform repetitive tasks (macro recording)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Provide a UI with a low barrier to entry
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          GIMP should be easily extensible by the average user: one
          click-installation of plug-ins
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <para>
      Minutes written by Roman Joost and Raphaël Quinet. Photos by
      Jean + Karine Delvare and Raphaël Quinet.
    </para>
 </section>

</webpage>
