<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
                         "dtd/website.dtd">

<webpage id="gimpcon2006" lang="en">
  
  <head>
    <title>The GIMP Developers Conference 2006</title>
    <titleabbrev>GIMPCon 2006</titleabbrev>
    <summary>This year's GimpCon</summary>
  </head>
  
  <para>
    The GIMP was part of the <ulink
    url="http://www.libregraphicsmeeting.org">Libre Graphics
      Meeting
    </ulink>
    held in Lyon from 17th to 19th of March.
  </para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Whats Next: Things to do for GIMP 2.4</title>
   
    <section>
      
    <title>SIOX</title> 
      
      <para>
        There are still performance concerns and features missing
        with SIOX.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Implement a low resolution preview for large images.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Implement a detail refinement brush.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            New preview toggle, which temporarily disables the automatic
            computation for multiple brush strokes for example.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A volunteer for this is needed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Tools</title>
      
      <para>
        Sven pointed out that the rectangular and ellipse selection
        tools should behave similar. The new align tool which is also
        confusing sometimes. It still behaves to flaky. The code for the
        Lanczos interpolation is currently broken.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Either fix the Lanczos code or hide it from the 2.4 release by
        removing it from the UI.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Googles Summer of Code</title>

      <para>
        Dave pointed out that the Summer of Code is coming soon were
        ideas are needed. GIMP is one of the projects which can offer
        tasks to be solved.
      </para>

      <para>
        Ideas and Tasks are needed at the beginning of May.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Preparations for 2.4</title>

      <para>
        Michael pointed out, that some terms the GIMP UI uses are
        misleading and very different from other image manipulation
        programs. One example is the misleading dpi instead of ppi.
      </para>

      <para>
        Michael proposed a Texttool PDB and also new features: multiple
        styles for a line of text, more control over text.
        Unfortunately, GIMP doesn't support currently all pango
        features. Sometimes Ligature problems with Bitstream Vera Sans
        occur.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A list of blocker bugs for the 2.4 release is needed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A string and UI freeze is needed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Mitchs cleanup should not be commited before 2.4 release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Volunteers are needed for checking GIMP terms (English and
            translations). A wiki page should track the termans and also
            possible translations. One volunteer should elaborate if
            Rosetta from Ubuntu can be used for this.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A bug is needed for plug-ins which use g_message() and where
            dialogs pop up behind the main window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A volunteer is needed for the Texttool PDB.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>
      The manual currently features nine languages, five are activly
      worked on. Russian and Norwegian will be added after the 0.10
      release. DocBook/XML is a barrier for new contributors, but there
      is currently no valuable alternative available.
    </para>

    <para>
      For PDF creation we should use dblatex instead of the dead project
      db2latex.
    </para>

    <para>
      The more translation an XML file holds the more difficult it is
      for contributors to concentrate on their content. Maybe we should
      split up the content directory-wise instead of profiling.
    </para>

    <para>
      Michael proposed way users can comment on HTML pages like the PHP
      documentation. The problems are: what will happen to comments
      after an update of the documentation, how and who manages
      comments, which system will suit our needs.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <title>TODO</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Stick to DocBook/XML for the next year. Be aware of the
          problems and change to a different internal structure if
          needed. A new project page should make it easier to
          contributors to join the project.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Elaborate which issue tracker can lower the barriers for
          feedback from our readers.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
 
  <section>
    <title>GIMP 2.99</title>

    <section>
      <title>GEGL</title>

      <para>
        Pippin pointed out, that GEGL does not yet support calculation
        over regions of interest. Some of the code that does that is
        currently 8-bits only, but the reference buffer implementation
        would be 32bits float per pixel. Yosh proposed to generate all
        the code needed for this from a template.
      </para>

      <para>
        Mitch suggested, that the integration of GEGL should be in small
        steps. The plug-in API should be GEGL only, but will provide
        backwards compatibility from old plug-ins for 8bits only.
      </para>

      <para>
        UI and Usability problems are also caused by the indexed mode.
        We concluded, that it should be available if the user exports
        his image to an indexed format, like GIF.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Write the 32bits float version first, then generate others
            from that reference version.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Replace the code in the base directory by GEGL operations.
            First replace the image map tool (used for color correction,
            etc.) using GEGL adapters around the pixel buffers. Then
            later replace the layers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How can we Motivate People to Join the GIMP Development?</title>

    <para>
      The current project page for gimp.org is not really structured and
      not very easy to get in touch with the developers. The GIMP
      developers should setup a tasks list in which they consider they
      are easy to solve and useful for the next version. Some of them
      can be used for Googles Summer of Code.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <title>TODO</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Setup a tasks list on the wiki of what can be achieved and
          implemented. It ranges from easy to very complex tasks. A bug
          on bugzilla for each task should be filed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</webpage>
